Terra (Portuguese for land)
Terra( 葡 萄 牙 語 ﹚ 陸 地
This was an age of important geographic discoveries.
這 是 一 個 地 理 大 發 現 的 時 代
Westerners used their knowledge in navigation
西 方 人 帶 著 航 海 知 識 的 優 勢
to sail the world.
席 捲 全 世 界
With them came opportunities for cultural contacts.
他 們 帶 來 了 文 化 接 觸 的 機 會
The navigators also gave name to a
同 時 也 讓 東 方 一 座 海 上 小 島
beautiful small island in the Pacific.
有 了 美 麗 的 封 號
During the 14th century,
十 囤 世 紀
the Renaissance movement spread across Western Europe.
西 歐 興 起 了 文 藝 復 興 運 動
The Renaissance emphasized
這 股 文 藝 復 興 思 潮
rational thinking,
強 調 理 性 怒 維
which nurtured humanism and the spirit of science,
孕 育 了 人 文 主 義 和 科 學 精 神
and changed Europe's perspectives
改 變 了 當 時 代 歐 洲 人 的
of life and the cosmos.
人 生 觀 和 宇 宙 觀
During the 15th to the 17th centuries,
也 開 啟 了 十 五 世 紀 到 十 七 世 紀
the Renaissance also led to the advent of the age of great navigations.
人 類 向 遠 洋 挑 戰 的 大 航 海 時 代
In 1488, Portuguese navigator Diaz discovered
1488 年 葡 萄 牙 航 海 家 狂 亞 士
Cape Town.
發 現 好 望 角
In 1492, Spanish navigator Columbus discovered
1492 年 西 班 牙 航 海 家 哥 倫 布
the Americas.
發 現 北 美 新 大 陸
In 1498, Portuguese navigator da Gama discovered
1498 年 葡 蒟 牙 航 海 家 達 伽 馬
a new navigational route in the Indian Ocean.
開 拓 印 度 洋 新 航 路
In 1499, Italian navigator Vespucci discovered
1499 年 義 大 利 航 海 家 亞 美 利 哥
South America.
發 現 南 美 洲
In 1519, Portuguese navigator Magellan sailed around the
1519 年 葡 蒟 牙 航 海 家 麥 哲 倫
southern tip of the Americas, passing through the Pacific
繞 過 美 洲 最 南 端
Ocean and arriving at Luzon island of the Philippines.
經 過 太 平 洋 到 達 菲 律 窗 呂 宋 島
With geographical discoveries
隨 著 地 理 大 發 現
and the opening of new sea routes,
和 新 航 路 的 開 闢
men entered the age of sea powers.
人 類 進 入 海 權 時 代
European countries along the Atlantic Ocean
歐 洲 大 西 洋 沿 岸 的 國 家
used their knowledge in navigation
利 用 航 海 知 識 的 優 勤
to sail the world.
席 捲 全 世 界
Attracted by huge profit
也 為 了
from spice trading,
﹁ 香 料 貿 易 」 的 巨 大 利 益 誘 囡
they came to Asia.
紛 紛 來 到 了 亞 洲
During the great navigation age in the 16th century,
十 六 世 紀 大 航 海 時 代
western fleets arrived in Asia.
西 方 船 隊 相 繼 來 到 亞 洲
Trade between the East and the West became frequent.
東 西 方 的 海 上 貿 易 越 來 越 蓬 勃
Yet the Ming Dynasty during that time
但 是 當 時 的 中 國 明 朝 政 府
adopted stringent policies to ban maritime trade.
卻 掌 取 嚴 厲 的 海 禁 政 策
The Ming administration only accepted tributes offered by
只 接 受 各 國 向 中 國 朝 貢
other countries and refused trade with other countries.
拒 絕 與 他 國 貿 易
This emboldened ambitious
困 此 造 就 了
seafarers to compete
各 股 海 上 聖 雄 的 勢 力
for huge business profits.
競 逐 龐 大 的 商 業 利 益
First,
首 先
Japanese businessmen ventured south
日 本 商 人 紛 紛 南 下
to trade in Formosa.
到 福 爾 摩 沙 進 行 貿 易
From their Macao base, Portuguese
以 澳 門 為 根 據 地 的 葡 萄 牙 人
traveled northbound passing through Pescadores.
則 經 過 澎 湖 北 上
On their way to trade in Japan.
前 往 日 本 經 商
Along the coastal areas in China,
而 當 時 中 國 沿 海 的
smuggling by trader groups
海 商 海 盜 集 團 的 走 私 買 易
was likewise rampant.
也 相 當 的 活 躍
In addition,
緊 接 著
Spanish merchants based in the Philippines and
以 菲 律 窗 為 根 據 地 的 西 班 牙
the Dutch East India Company,
和 以 東 南 亞 為 基 礎 的
which was based in southeast Asia,
﹁ 荷 蘭 聯 合 東 印 度 公 司 」
started to develop trade relations
也 開 始 開 發 與 中 國 的
with China.
各 種 貿 易 關 傢
In this sea trading network,
在 這 個 海 上 貿 易 網 路 中
the sea routes near Formosa
福 爾 摩 沙 附 近 海 域
became indispensable to the foreign sea merchants.
成 了 各 國 航 運 必 經 之 地
Foreign fleets often times
各 國 船 隊 之 間
intercepted and sacked one another
常 常 為 了 商 業 利 益 的 競 爭
due to commercial interests,
彼 此 攔 截 掠 奪
which led to increasing conflicts.
衝 突 日 益 加 大
Formosa
福 爾 摩 沙
during that time remained
在 當 時 還 是 一 個
an untouched paradise,
混 汐 未 開 的 世 外 桃 源
a land without ruler.
是 一 塊 無 主 地
Formosa was unlike China and Japan,
既 不 像 中 國 和 日 本 那 樣
where autonomous administrations existed.
已 經 形 成 自 主 有 力 的 政 治 實 體
Neither was Formosa like Ryukyu and Korea,
也 不 同 於 琉 球 和 朝 鮮
which were afforded political
從 屬 在 龐 大 的 大 明 帝 國 的
protection by the Ming Empire.
政 治 庇 護 之 下
During the early 17th century,
當 十 七 世 紀 初 期
the orient seas bustled with trade.
東 洋 海 域 逐 漸 熟 鬮 起 來
Western powers, oriental traders, and Japanese pirates
西 方 勢 力 以 及 東 方 海 商 和 倭 寇
established strongholds
陸 續 在 福 爾 摩 沙
in Formosa in succession.
設 立 重 要 據 點 時
The island of Formosa, which was located
位 於 東 亞 海 上 交 通 要 道 的
at the thoroughfare of the seas in southeast Asia,
福 爾 摩 沙 島
thus emerged into the world scene
在 歷 史 潮 流 的 推 波 助 瀾 下
driven by the tides of history.
首 度 登 上 了 國 際 舞 臺
After the Portuguese and Spaniards,
繼 葡 萄 牙 人 和 西 班 牙 人 之 後
the Dutch in 1625 was finally
1625 年 荷 蘭 人 終 於 畫 出 一 張
able to draft a more comprehensive map of Formosa.
比 較 完 整 的 福 爾 摩 沙 地 圖
As a result, Formosa became known to the world.
福 爾 摩 沙 也 困 此 被 世 界 認 識
Established in 1602,
成 立 於 1602 年 的
the Dutch East India Company
﹁ 荷 蘭 聯 合 東 印 度 公 司 」
was a trading monopoly
是 個 具 有 駐 在 地 外 交 權 的
with diplomatic powers in the countries of residence.
國 家 特 許 公 司
The company was bestowed
公 司 被 賦 予 統 治 權
the power to rule and military power.
軍 事 權 等 國 家 權 力
In 1622, after being defeated in Macao
1622 年 荷 蘭 艦 隊 在 澳 門 之 役
by the Portuguese,
敗 給 葡 蒟 牙 之 後
the Dutch fleet arrived at Pescadores.
糠 往 澎 湖
The Dutch East India Company,
荷 印 公 司 接 受 當 時 最 有 勢 力 的
upon recommendation from Chinese pirate-trader
華 人 海 盜 海 商 李 旦
Li Tan and Hsu Hsin-su,
以 及 許 心 素 的 建 議
and with tacit consent from the Hsiamen military commander
在 1624 年 得 到 廈 門 總 兵 的 默 許
in 1624, retreated from Pescadores to Formosa.
從 澎 湖 撤 退 到 福 爾 摩 沙
During then, the Ming Empire
那 時 大 明 帝 國 對 福 爾 摩 沙
did not have explicit rule over Formosa.
並 沒 有 明 磐 的 統 治 權
The Dutch company thus again landed in
於 是 荷 印 公 司 就 二 度 在 大 員 島
Tayuan Island, which is present-day Anping in Tainan,
也 就 是 今 天 台 南 安 平 登 陸
and began its 38-year
開 始 了 對 福 爾 摩 沙 島
colonization of Formosa.
三 十 八 年 的 殖 民 式 統 治
The Dutch were skilled
當 時 荷 蘭 是 個
castle builders.
善 於 建 造 城 堡 的 國 家
They recruited many Han workers
他 們 從 大 陸 沿 海
from coastal regions of China
招 募 大 量 漢 人 民 工
to build Fort Zeelandia
建 造 了 ﹁ 熱 蘭 遮 城 」
and Fort Provintia.
和 ﹁ 普 羅 民 適 城 」 兩 座 城 填
To this day, the two castles have survived battles
這 兩 座 城 堡 歷 經 戰 火 洗 禮
and undergone reconstructions through the years.
與 各 朝 代 改 建 存 留 至 今
They are the predecessors of Anping Fort and
成 了 今 天 ﹁ 安 平 古 堡 」
the Chihkan Tower of today.
和 ﹁ 赤 崁 樓 」 的 前 身
The Dutch used the two castles
荷 蘭 人 在 當 時
as stronghold
就 以 這 兩 座 城 作 為 據 點
to rapidly expand to the north and south
迅 速 向 南 北 擴 張
to colonize Taiwan.
對 台 灣 進 行 殖 民 統 治
The Dutch company's rule over Formosa
荷 印 公 司 在 福 爾 摩 沙 的 統 治
was gradually reinforced through military actions.
隨 著 軍 事 行 動 而 逐 漸 載 固
The company created the Council of Formosa
公 司 以 ﹁ 大 員 評 議 會 」
to rule Taiwan.
作 為 統 轄 台 灣 的 領 主
Under the Council was Zeelandia City,
下 面 管 轄 熬 蘭 遮 市
the municipal court and local assembly.
﹁ 市 政 法 庭 」 和 ﹁ 地 方 議 會 」
The municipal court represented
﹁ 市 政 法 庭 」
all city residents,
是 市 民 總 體 的 代 表 機 關
while the local assembly represented
﹁ 地 方 議 會 」 則 是
all the aboriginal tribes.
原 住 民 村 落 的 總 體 代 表 機 關
The Dutch governed the island
荷 蘭 人 以 重 商 主 義 的 原 則
focusing on the importance of commerce.
治 理 島 上 的 人 民
Resistance from the aborigines was met
對 於 原 住 民 的 反 抗
with harsh retaliation.
就 給 予 強 烈 報 復
They repressed resistance in Matou and Hsiaolung.
曾 在 麻 豆 、 蕭 壞 兩 地 進 行 鎮 壓
During the same time,
同 一 時 期
Dutch missionaries also
荷 蘭 的 傳 教 士
actively engaged in missionary work
也 積 極 在 福 爾 摩 沙 南 部
in southern Formosa.
展 開 傳 教 工 作
The missionaries built schools and used
創 建 學 校
Roman scripts to translate the Bible and prayers
以 羅 馬 挖 音 寫 平 埔 族 語 的
into the dialect of the plain-dwelling aborigines.
聖 經 、 前 禱 文 等 等
The use of Roman scripts later became popular among
這 種 拼 音 文 字
the plain-dwelling aborigines.
後 來 在 平 埔 族 中 廣 為 流 傳
The scripts were frequently used to draft contracts with
經 常 3 被 用 來 和 華 人 寫 契 約
the Han people, the so-called Hsinkang manuscript.
這 就 是 所 謂 的 ﹁ 新 港 文 書 」
Due to the Dutch rule of Formosa,
由 於 荷 蘭 對 福 爾 摩 沙 的 統 治
other countries became ill at ease.
引 起 了 其 他 各 國 的 不 安
Two years after the Dutch
在 荷 蘭 人 佔 領
occupied the south of Formosa,
福 爾 摩 沙 南 部 之 後 兩 年
the Spanish fleet in May 1626
1626 年 5 月 西 班 牙 也 派 軍 隊
arrived at the sea off Santiago Bay
拯 達 福 爾 摩 沙 東 北 海 岸 的
in northeastern Formosa.
三 貔 角 灣 外 海
The Spaniards occupied Chilong
先 是 佔 領 雞 籠
and held a ceremony of occupation on Sheliao Island.
接 著 在 社 寧 島 舉 行 佔 領 儀 式
The Spaniards built
並 且 在 島 上 建 造 一 座
Fort San Salvador on the island,
聖 薩 爾 瓦 多 垢
and proclaimed their
宣 告 對 福 爾 摩 沙 島 的
symbolic rule of Formosa.
象 徵 性 統 治
In 1628, the Spaniards built
1628 年 西 班 牙 人 在 滬 尾
Fort San Domingo
也 就 是 今 天 的 淡 水
in present-day Tamsui.
建 造 一 座 ﹁ 聖 多 明 哥 城 」
This was the origin of the
這 就 是 今 天
Hungmaocheng in Tamsui, or City of the Red-Haired,.
淡 水 ﹁ 紅 毛 垢 」 的 由 來
The Spaniards used Fort San Domingo
西 班 牙 人 把 ﹁ 聖 多 明 哥 城 」
as a relay station in sea navigation,
當 成 航 運 的 中 繼 站
as well as a center for ruling
以 及 統 治 平 埔 族
the plain-dwelling aborigines and Han people.
和 漢 人 的 中 心
At the same time,
同 時
the fort served as a fortress for Spanish colonization.
也 是 西 班 牙 殖 民 地 的 軍 事 要 塞
The Spanish church demanded tributes from the aborigines,
西 班 牙 教 會 要 求 原 住 民 納 須
and later incorporated present-day Taipei basin
最 後 將 現 在 台 北 盆 地
and the northeastern coast
和 福 爾 摩 沙 東 北 海 岸
into their jurisdiction.
都 納 入 他 們 的 勢 力 範 圍
The Spaniards ruled and spread religion.
進 行 統 治 及 傳 教
Due to the war with Muslims
由 於
in Luzon, the Spaniards moved
西 班 牙 在 呂 宋 和 穆 斯 林 作 戰
their forces to southern Luzon in the Philippines
把 軍 隊 移 防 呂 宋 南 部
and decided to concentrate on ruling Luzon.
並 決 定 專 心 經 營 呂 宋
The Spaniards in 1638
1638 年 西 班 牙 人 毀 去 滬 尾 的
destroyed Fort San Domingo in Tamsui.
﹁ 聖 多 明 哥 城 」
In 1642, the Dutch drove the Spaniards out of Taiwan
1642 年 荷 蘭 取 代 了 西 班 牙
and ended Spain's 16-year
結 束 西 班 牙
rule of northern Formosa.
在 福 爾 摩 沙 島 北 部 的 十 公 年 統 治
Another faction composed
另 一 股 以 華 人 為 主
mainly of Chinese, a few Japanese,
和 少 數 的 日 本 人
and Portuguese
和 葡 菏 牙 人 合 組 而 成 的 勢 力
emerged in the meantime.
也 在 這 同 時 螈 起
This was a group of traders and pirates that engaged
他 們 是 兼 具 海 商 和 海 盜 身 分 的
in maritime smuggling.
海 上 走 私 貿 易 集 團
Among them, Lin Tao-kan, Lin Feng, Li Tan,
其 中 林 道 乾 、 林 鳳 、 李 旦
Yen Ssu-chi, and Cheng Chih-lung
顏 怒 齊 、 鄭 芝 龍
used Chiayi and Peikang as their stronghold.
常 以 嘉 義 和 北 港 為 據 點
The scope of their activities
活 動 範 圍 甚 至 到 達 日 本
extended to Japan, the Philippines, and Indonesia.
菲 律 窗 和 印 尼
Among these prominent personalities,
在 這 些 叱 吒 風 雲 的 人 物 當 中
the rise of Cheng Chih-lung
鄭 芝 龍 的 螈 起
had significant impact
尤 其 影 響 了
on the later developments of Taiwan.
台 灣 本 來 歷 史 的 發 展
Cheng had a son with a Japanese woman
他 和 日 本 女 子 田 川 氏 生 下
named Tagawa. Their son, Fusung,
幼 名 ﹁ 福 松 」 的 茹 子
was to become Cheng Cheng-kung,
這 個 孩 子 就 是 後 來
who would change Taiwan's history.
改 變 台 灣 歷 史 的 鄭 成 功
The young Cheng Chih-lung
鄭 芝 龍 年 輕 時
once worked as an interpreter
曾 經 擔 任 過
for Dutch Commander Cornelis Reijersen.
荷 蘭 司 令 雷 爾 生 的 通 譯
Cheng inherited Li Tan's
他 首 先 接 收 了
power after Li's death.
海 商 李 旦 死 後 的 勢 力
He also pledged allegiance to the Ming Dynasty,
後 來 也 接 受 明 朝 政 府 招 降
and thus was later able to eradicate the other pirates
進 而 名 正 言 順 地 消 滅 其 他 海 蜀
and become a formidable force
成 為 縱 橫 中 國 東 南 海 域
on the seas southeast of China.
最 強 大 的 海 上 勢 力
In 1644, the Ching forces invaded China.
1644 年 清 兵 入 關
Sensing the demise of the Ming Dynasty,
睦 看 大 明 常 國 大 夥 已 去
Cheng traveled north to surrender to the Ching power.
鄭 芝 龍 北 上 接 受 清 政 府 招 降
He was, however, detained.
不 料 卻 反 被 軟 禁
His son Cheng Cheng-kung continued
他 的 兒 子 鄭 成 功
to use Kinmen and Hsiamen as bases to fight against
仍 然 持 續 以 金 門 、 廈 門
Ching administration and restore the Ming Dynasty.
作 為 反 清 復 明 的 基 地
On Nov. 30, 1646,
1646 年 11 月 30 日
Ching attacked Cheng Chih-lung's base at Anping.
清 軍 突 襲 鄭 芝 龍 的 安 平 基 地
They burned and plundered.
燒 殺 搔 掠
Tagawa, who had been separated for 13 years
和 鄭 成 功 分 別 了 十 三 年
and had recently reunited with her son,
才 團 聚 的 母 親 田 川 氏
committed suicide to avoid disgrace.
為 了 免 於 被 辱 自 殺
A traumatized Cheng Cheng-kung
國 破 家 亡 下 的 鄭 成 功
decided to burn
痛 下 決 心
his scholar clothes
以 焦 燒 儒 服 的 方 式
to pursue a military career,
表 明 自 己 棄 文 從 武
and show his absolute determination.
肯 水 一 戰 的 心 志
In 1659,
1659 年
after a major defeat in Nanking,
鄭 成 功 南 京 一 役 大 敗 之 後
Cheng retreated to Hsiamen
迴 回 廈 門
to regroup his forces
重 新 整 頓 軍 隊
in preparation for the next offensive.
預 備 下 一 次 的 反 攻 行 動
A former interpreter of the
曾 經 在 福 爾 摩 汪
Dutch East India Company,
擔 任 荷 印 公 司 通 事 的 何 斌
Ho Pin, absconded to Hsiamen to evade creditors.
困 為 躲 避 債 務
Ho presented a map of the island of Taiwan,
來 到 廈 門 獻 上 ﹁ 台 灣 島 」
then called Tayuan Island,
也 就 是 當 時 的 ﹁ 大 員 島 」 地 圖
and used the island's abundant resources
用 豐 富 的 物 產 來 遊 說 鄭 成 功
to persuade Cheng to invade Tayuan.
攻 打 大 員
Agonizing over provisions,
正 為 缺 乏 軍 糧 發 愁 的 鄭 成 功
Cheng readily accepted Ho's proposal.
欣 然 採 納 了 何 斌 的 建 議
On April 29, 1661,
1661 年 4 月 29 日
Cheng, a talented military strategist,
善 於 軍 事 謀 略 的 鄭 成 功
knew that the Luerhmen waterway would be too shallow and narrow
算 準 了 鹿 耳 門 水 道 既 淺 又 窄
for large ships to enter,
大 船 不 容 易 駛 入
and that there were no Dutch sentries on site.
荷 軍 沒 有 派 兵 防 守
So despite wind and rain,
於 是 冒 著 連 夜 風 需
he led his fleet
率 領 大 軍 分 別 搭 乘
of more than over 300 ships
三 百 多 艘 船 艦
to rush to Luerhman from Pescadores.
自 澎 湖 飛 渡 鹿 耳 門
On April 30, 1661 at dawn,
1661 年 4 月 30 日 清 晨
Cheng arrived at Luerhmen.
鄭 軍 拗 達 鹿 耳 門
He ordered his officers
鄭 成 功 立 即 命 令 官 兵 架 設 香 案
to set up an altar
淨 身 衰 禱
to pray for divine help.
前 求 天 助
Cheng chose to use Luerhmen waterway
鄭 成 功 選 擇 自 鹿 耳 門 水 道
to launch a surprise offensive on the inner sea at Taichiang
突 圓 台 江 內 海
because Luerhmen was vulnerable
主 要 是 困 為 鹿 耳 門 沒 有 設 防
against a surprise attack.
可 以 攻 其 不 備
The element of surprise could
也 可 以 出 奇 制 勝
also help Cheng avoid heavy fire from Fort Zeelandia and
避 開 火 力 強 大 的 熟 蘭 遨 城 炮 火
attack Fort Provintia instead.
突 襲 普 羅 民 遨 垢
After praying, Cheng had the water depth tested,
鄭 成 功 拜 完 立 刻 派 人 探 測 水 深
and the water had indeed risen by over three meters.
果 然 回 報 水 深 加 漲 了 一 丈 多
Cheng knew that it was the first day of the lunar month
鄭 成 功 深 知 那 天 是 農 曆 初 一
and that the tide would rise,
會 有 大 潮
helping his ships to sail in easily.
鄭 軍 船 艦 可 以 長 驅 直 入
Yet, he burned incense and prayed.
卻 依 然 焚 香 裕 禱
His purpose was to lead his soldiers
他 的 用 意 其 實 是 要 讓 官 兵
to believe that there was divine help,
以 為 得 到 天 助
and it raised morale.
以 激 勵 士 氣
German surveyor Philip Meij
德 國 土 地 測 量 師 梅 氏
had lived in Formosa for 19 years and worked
是 一 位 在 福 爾 摩 沙 住 了 十 九 年
for Dutch East India Company.
恒 聘 於 荷 印 公 司 的 專 業 人 員
Through his diary,
途 過 他 的 日 記
we come to understand that
我 們 更 深 刻 了 解 那 一 場
the battle was to decide Taiwan's destiny.
決 定 後 來 台 灣 命 運 的 歷 史 戰 役
Last day of April 1661.
1661 年 4 月 最 後 一 天
About 10 a.m. Saturday.
星 期 六 上 午 約 十 點 鐘
I was at the Han hospital
我 在 赤 崁 普 羅 民 遮 市 鎮 外 面 的
outside Provintia instructing masons
漢 人 醫 院 指 示 幾 個 水 泥 匠
working on the front gate.
建 造 大 門 的 地 方 時
Suddenly I saw flags floating on the castle in Tayuan.
突 然 看 到 大 員 城 堡 上 飄 著 旗 子
I thought
那 時 我 想
the commander wanted to ferry back.
大 概 是 長 官 閣 下 要 渡 航 來 此
So, I went to Provintia.
我 就 去 普 羅 民 遨 市 鎮
There I heard the news that
在 那 裡 聽 見 大 家 說
hundreds of junk ships led by Koxinga had arrived
國 姚 爺 率 領 數 百 艘 戎 克 船
at Luerhmen harbor.
來 到 鹿 耳 門 港 道
Deputy Governor Jacob Valentyn
地 方 官 貓 難 實 叮
hurried back from Tayuan.
也 已 從 大 員 趕 回 來 了
So I went to Fort Provintia.
於 是 我 去 普 羅 民 遨 城 城 堯
There were many junk ships.
我 克 船 很 多
I wasn't able to count the ships in my haste.
匆忙 之 間 無 法 計 數 量
Several ships
也 看 見 其 中 幾 艘
have already entered Luerhmen harbor.
己 經 駛 入 鹿 耳 門 港 道
I simply couldn't believe
我 簡 直 無 法 相 俸
how the ships were able to
那 又 窄 又 淺 的 水 道
pass through those narrow and shallow waterways.
竟 然 可 以 讓 帆 船 通 遇
Koxinga's forces were unchallenged
在 我 們 的 注 視 下
right before our eyes.
毫 無 遭 遇 扺 抗 地
His forces landed beside the brick kiln in Chaitou Pier,
他 們 的 士 兵 在 距 離 普 羅 民 遨 城
about 15 minutes or one kilometer
約 十 五 分 鐘 路 程 大 約 一 公 里 半
from Provintia.
染 頭 港 的 磚 點 旁 邊 登 陸
The enemy was in full battle gear.
敵 人 全 副 武 裝
From Jan Sou farm beside Hsin Kang-che Road,
士 氣 高 昂 地 從 位 於 新 港 車 路 旁
they marched over the hill in high morale
Jan Sou 的 農 園
amid the sounds of military drums and horns.
越 過 高 地 擊 鼓 吹 管 行 軍 而 來
Their troops had countless
他 們 的 軍 隊 有 數 不 完 的
colorful banners.
漂 亮 絲 質 旗 幟
Their helmets were shiny.
頭 戴 光 亳 的 頭 盔
They had broad swords.
手 握 大 刀
They traveled fast along Inding Street,
迅 連 沿 Inding 的 路
They passed through Hagena Forest
經 過 哈 根 那 森 林
and arrived at the small forest by the sea.
來 到 海 邊 的 小 森 林
They camped behind the small river north of Provintia.
普 羅 民 遨 城 北 邊 小 溪 後 面 紮 營
They set up thousands of tents.
在 那 裡 搭 起 千 百 個 帳 篷
It was 1:30 p.m.
時 間 是 下 午 一 點 半
Cheng quickly secured the
鄭 成 功 很 快 就 掌 握 了
navigation route between Tayuan and Chihkan.
大 員 和 赤 崁 之 間 航 道
They quickly prepared for an attack on the fort.
迅 速 展 開 陸 地 攻 城 的 準 備
I start to heard my subordinates
我 的 部 下 當 中 聽 到
complaint about hunger and thirst.
第 一 個 飢 餓 和 口 渴 拖 怨 的 聲 音
I went up the fort
我 上 去 城 堡
to get some food
要 去 為 他 們 和 我 自 己 取 一 些
for them and for myself.
吃 的 和 喝 的 東 西
When I got there, oh god!
但 是 到 了 那 裡 天 听
The cook was complaining even more.
那 廝 師 拖 怨 得 更 厲 害 了
He told me that
他 告 訴 我
the well was dried up.
二 裡 完 全 沒 不 到 水 了
Deputy Governor Valentyn,
普 羅 民 遨 城 行 政 長 官 貓 難 實 叮
faced with water and food shortage,
在 嚴 重 缺 水 與 缺 糧 食 等 壓 力 下
finally decided to abandon the fort.
終 於 決 定 棄 城
Cheng moved his forces in,
讓 鄭 成 功 大 軍 進 駐
and secured his first victory.
贏 得 第 一 步 勝 利 之 後
For his next step,
下 一 步
Cheng planned to take down Fort Zeelandia.
鄭 成 功 就 想 拿 下 熟 蘭 遮 垢 了
He offered acceptance to surrender to Fort Zeelandia,
他 一 面 向 熟 蘭 遮 城 招 降
and sent his troops to besiege
一 面 自 北 線 、
the fort from the north, the sea,
海 面 、 及 大 員 三 個 方 囝
and Tayuan.
以 圍 城 姿 勢 進 逼 熟 蘭 遮 城
Cheng knew that with the southwestern wind blowing,
鄭 成 功 算 準 西 南 季 風 期 間
the Dutch fleet could not travel to its
荷 蘭 船 艦 無 法 航 向
headquarters in Batavia, Indonesia, to seek help.
位 於 印 尼 總 部 的
So he left a smaller force
巴 達 維 亞 城 求 救
to lay long-term siege to the fort,
所 以 只 派 少 數 兵 力 長 期 圍 城
while sending the mass of his forces to work on farmlands.
大 多 數 軍 隊 分 派 下 去 屯 田
Cheng had planned for an enduring war.
他 已 經 有 持 久 戰 的 心 理 準 備 了
He wrote endless letters to
鄭 成 功 不 斷 寫 倌
Tayuan chief Frederic Coyett to convince him to surrender.
給 大 員 長 官 撮 一 勸 他 投 降
On May 24, 1661,
1661 年 5 月 24 日
Cheng ordered a letter written in Dutch
鄭 成 功 命 人 用 荷 蘭 文 寫 了 一 封 信
to be delivered by the
派 被 他 俘 虜 的 荷 蘭 妤 師 亨 佟 魯 克
captured Dutch missionary Antonius Hambroek
到 鳥 特 勒 支 碉堡
to Coyett at Fort Utrecht.
送 俸 給 揍 一
Hambroek was supposed to
亨 伯 魯 克 政 師 身 為 勸 降 特 使
convince Coyett to surrender,
不 但 沒 有 勸 熱 蘭 遮 城 長 官 撮 一 投 降
but instead he convinced Coyett to battle on until
反 而 勸 他 們 抗 戰 到 底
reinforcement arrived from the Batavia headquarters.
等 巴 達 維 亞 總 部 派 援 軍 來
I am well aware
我 很 清 楚
that saying this means the end for me,
我 說 這 話 等 於 是 宣 告 我 的 死 刑
but I cannot discharge my obligations
然 而 我 絕 不 會 困 為 畏 縮 而 忘 卻
to God and the company if I cower.
我 對 上 常 和 公 司 的 義 務
I would rather take a thousand risks,
我 寧 願 冒 一 千 次
putting me and my wife in physical danger,
我 和 我 妻 子 生 命 的 危 險
than allow myself to be used by the enemy.
也 不 願 為 敵 人 所 利 用
I would not betray God,
不 類 成 為 育 叛 上 常
and be a traitor to my country.
和 同 胞 的 賣 國 賊
From Aug. 11 to 12, 1661,
1661 年 8 月 11 到 12 日
an armada of 10 Dutch ships
十 艙 荷 蘭 船 和 一 艘 帆 船
and a sail boat
所 組 成 的 荷 蘭 艦 隊
appeared at sea in Tayuan.
出 現 在 大 員 海 面
Cheng was shocked because
鄭 成 功 大 驕 失 色
he had sent most of
困 為 他 的 士 兵 幾 乎 全 數
his troops to cultivate land in different places,
洙 到 各 地 去 開 壅
and it was impossible to recall them.
根 本 抽 調 不 回 來
Fortunately the weather turned bad,
幸 好 天 氣 變 壤
and the Dutch armada took shelter in Pescadores.
荷 蘭 艦 隊 到 澎 湖 避 風
Our hope vanished.
我 們 的 希 望 泡 湯 了
There was a strong wind.
刪 來 一 陣 強 風
The weather was getting worse.
天 氣 變 壞
Our ships were forced to leave.
我 們 的 艦 隊 不 得 不 離 開
Worse, the next day we heard
更 糟 糕 的 是 隔 日 聽 到
that Urck ran aground near Masha Channel.
那 艘 Urck 號 在 馬 沙 溝 附 近 擱 淺
Everyone onboard was captured by the enemy.
船 上 所 有 的 人 都 被 敵 人 活 捉
September
9 月
Calm weather enabled
涇 象 終 於 恢復 平 靜
the Dutch armada to enter Zeelandia.
荷 蘭 艦 隊 才 能 駛 入 熟 蘭 遮 城
But Cheng used
但 是 鄭 成 功
his many lighter,
又 利 用 自 己 船 又 輕 又 多
shallow-water ships
吃 水 又 淺 的 優 點
to again win the battle.
打 了 一 場 勝 仗
In the sea battle in Taikang on Sept. 16,
﹁ 九 一 六 台 江 海 戰 」
Cheng's strategy
鄭 軍 的 戰 術
was to fire cannons from land and sea
是 從 海 陸 兩 方 面 用 炮 還 擊
and send sail boats and gun ships
同 時 派 出 許 多 帆 船 和 火 船
to surround and attack the Dutch fleet.
去 圍 攻 荷 蘭 艦 隊
In the heat of the battle,
在 激 恬 戰 火 中
the Dutch's Kou Keren
荷 艦 ﹁ 柯 克 倫 號 」
was destroyed by Cheng's cannons.
被 鄭 軍 的 密 集 砲 火 打 碎
Another vessel ran aground
另 一 艘 ﹁ 科 登 霍 夫 號 」
and was destroyed
也 沖 攤 擱 淺
by a Chinese gun ship.
被 一 艘 中 國 火 船 燒 毀
After the crushing defeat on the inner sea at Taichiang,
台 江 內 海 慘 敗 之 後
Coyett and the Council of Formosa decided
大 員 甘 官 撬 一 和 評 議 會
to play the defensive.
決 議 改 採 守 勢
Jan. 17, 1662
1662 年 1 月 17 日
Those who had defected urged Koxinga
那 些 投 敵 者 極 力 勸 國 姓 爺
not to attack Fort Zeelandia,
不 要 去 攻 打 熱 蘭 遮 城 堡
but the people inside the fort wanted Cheng to attack.
垢 裡 的 人 就 是 希 望 他 們 去 攻 打
The defectors urged Cheng to attack Fort Utrecht,
要 先 去 攻 鳥 特 勒 支 碉堡
which was worth attacking.
那 是 最 值 得 攻 打 的
The next target would be the redoubt located at the beach,
然 後 去 攻 打 那 個 海 邊 的 木 柵
which would be easy to take down.
那 將 很 容 易 攻 取
Then, without losing many soldiers,
到 那 時 候 不 必 損 失 多 少 士 兵
it would be easy to capture the forte.
就 可 輕 易 的 奪 取 荷 蘭 狄 亞 稜 堡
And enter the city.
進 入 四 角 副 城
Within a short time,
在 短 時 間 內
it would be possible to place mines below the official residence
就 可 從 長 官 官 邸 的 地 下 室
in Amsterdam Bastion,
埋 地 雷 在 阿 姆 斯 特 丹 稜 堡 下 面
and blow up the entire place.
把 整 座 城 堡 炸 垮
Jan. 25, 1662,
1662 年 1 月 25 日
A cannon battle unprecedented
一 場 台 灣 史 上 空 前 的 大 炮 戰
in Taiwan's history began in the former Tayuan Island.
在 昔 日 的 大 員 島 展 開 了
Cheng's troops attacked Fort Utrecht
鄭 軍 全 面 攻 擊 鳥 特 勒 支 堯
with 30 big cannons.
用 三 十 門 大 砲
In the simultaneous attack on Fort Zeelandia
同 時 攻 擊 熟 蘭 遨 垢
and Fort Utrecht,
和 烏 特 勒 支 堯
Cheng's army fired 2500
鄭 軍 在 一 天 內 發 射 了
cannon shots in one day.
兩 千 五 百 發 砲 彈
They destroyed Fort Utrecht,
轟 毀 了 烏 特 勒 支 填
and totally smashed
也 徹 底 擊 垮 了
the Dutch's will to fight.
荷 蘭 人 的 戰 鬥 意 志
Jan. 30, 1662
1662 年 1 月 30 日
Under siege for 275 days,
被 圍 困 長 達 275 天 的 熟 蘭 遮 城
Fort Zeelandia finally opened its gates,
終 於 閔 城
and the Dutch relinquished their rule.
荷 蘭 人 交 出 統 治 權
This was the first transfer of power
這 是 台 灣 史 上
in Taiwan's history.
第 一 次 的 政 權 替 換
You have been under siege for nine months.
現 在 你 們 被 圍 城 九 個 月 了
The fault
一 切 的 錯 誤
is all yours.
都 是 你 們 自 己 尋 來 的
What else can you say?
還 有 什 麼 詩 說
Do you think I am satisfied
難 道 現 在 我 得 到 一 個 雕 堯
to have taken the fort?
我 就 會 滿 意 了 嗣
All you people who think you're smart
﹣ 條 ﹤ 衍 1 = 大 2 坌 灰 芝 x ﹒ 玲 y 干 志 日 口 史 刃 ﹣ 人 ﹍
can think about this.
可 以 自 己 想 想 看
We agree to surrender Castle Zeelandia and
我 們 同 意 殿 下
other properties belonging to the Company to Lord Koxinga,
將 城 堡 和 公 司 與 貨 物 都 交 給 你
except for the company's books, documents,
但 公 司 在 此 地 的 簿 記 、
and servants.
文 件 和 奴 隸 要 除 外
Also, we want to load and ship all articles needed
而 且 我 們 得 以 從 這 些 貨 物 中
by our personnel during
把 我 們 全 體 人 員 航 披 巴 達 維 亞
their voyage to Batavia.
所 需 要 的 物 品 先 行 裝 進 船 裡
We fully agree
關 於 要 照 你 們 的 習 慣
with your practice of
讓 軍 人 持 著 飛 揚 的 旗 子
letting your soldiers board the ships
燒 著 的 火 繩 子 彈 上 膛
with flying banners, burning fusees,
撤 退 上 船
and loaded rifles.
我 完 全 同 意
For your voyage to Batavia,
你 們 前 往 巴 達 維 亞 的 航 行
1 allow you to take the food, water,
所 霍 的 一 切 糧 食 、 飲 料
and ammunitions
彈 藥 等
you will need.
我 允 許 住 們 得 以 從 城 堡 裡 拿 去
I was released and ordered
馬 本 都 把 我 釋 放 了
to go with their hostages
並 命 令 我 跟 他 們 的 人 質
to Fort Zeelandia.
一 起 去 熟 蘭 遨 城 填
Among 300 people only three survived.
大 約 三 百 人 當 中 僅 存 的
One of them finally
三 個 人 之 一
returned to their friends,
終 於 又 回 到 他 的 朋 友 身 邊
back to Christians
回 到 基 督 徒 的 身 邊
Praise and thanks to God the almighty.
讚 美 尊 敬 慶 謝 那 位 萬 能 的 神
God protected me
祂 在 我 所 有 的 困 境 和 險 惡 時
in times of difficulty and danger.
神 奇 的 保 護 我
God let me regain freedom.
使 我 重 獲 自 由
Feb. 9, 1662
1662 年 2 月 9 日
Women and children
分 散 在 原 住 民 各 社 的
living in aboriginal villages
荷 蘭 婦 女 跟 兒 童
returned to Fort Zeelandia.
都 回 到 熬 蘭 遮 城
Led by Tayuan governor Coyett,
大 員 島 長 官 揆 一
over 900 soldiers in full battle gear marched
率 領 九 百 多 名 的 士 官 兵
out of Fort Zeelandia.
全 副 武 裝 走 出 熟 蘭 遮 城
Some 2000 Dutch soldiers and civilians
荷 蘭 軍 民 兩 千 人
boarded eight Dutch ships
分 別 登 上 八 觼 荷 蘭 船 艦
waiting to set sail.
等 候 出 航
Coyett surrendered the key to
搓 一 在 海 灘
Fort Zeelandia at the beach.
交 出 熟 蘭 遮 城 的 鑰 匙
Cheng led his soldiers
鄭 成 功 率 領 武 裝 士 兵
and entered Fort Zeelandia
從 已 經 毀 壞 的 鳥 特 勒 支 碉 填
through the ruined Fort Utrecht.
進 入 熟 蘭 遨 城
Cheng thus took over the Dutch East India Company.
接 收 東 印 度 公 司 的 財 產
This was the first transfer of power
寫 下 台 灣 史 上
in Taiwan's history.
第 一 次 政 權 交 替 的 一 頁
Feb. 17, 1662
1662 年 2 月 17 日
The last Tayuan governor Coyett
大 員 末 代 長 官 撬 一
led the Dutch army and civilians on their
率 領 荷 蘭 軍 民 返 航 巴 達 維 亞
return trip to Batavia;
結 束 ﹁ 荷 蘭 聯 合 東 印 度 公 司 」
thus, ending 38 years of colonial rule
在 福 爾 摩 沙 島 上
of Formosa island by the Dutch.
三 十 八 年 的 殖 民 統 治
On June 23, 1662
1662 年 6 月 23 日
The hero Cheng,
一 代 莢 雁 鄭 成 功
shortly after taking over Fort Zeelandia,
在 取 下 熟 蘭 遮 城 後 不 久
suddenly passed away.
就 突 然 去 遊
He was 39.
死 時 才 三 十 九 歲
Cheng was succeeded by his son Cheng Ching,
鄭 成 功 的 兒 子 鄭 經 接 續 了 王 位
who changed the island's name to Kingdom of Tungning.
把 國 號 封 為 東 寧 國
Because Cheng Cheng-kung stationed the military on farmlands,
鄭 成 功 時 代 囤 為 屯 田
the relations with the aborigines is tense.
和 原 住 民 的 關 係 十 分 綺 張
During Cheng Ching's time,
在 鄭 經 時 期
Han villages began to emerge rapidly;
漢 人 村 落 如 雨 後 春 笭 般 的 出 現
conflicts with aboriginals worsened.
和 原 住 民 的 衝 突 更 大
Troops were sent to subdue the aboriginal tribes.
困 此 出 動 軍 隊 討 伐 原 住 民 部 落
There were at least seven large-scale
有 記 載 的 大 規 模 軍 事 討 伐
military actions on record.
至 少 有 七 次
To totally eliminate
為 了 徹 底 去 除
the influence of Christianity,
基 督 教 文 化 的 影 響
churches were turned into temples.
教 堂 被 改 建 成 廈 宇
The Confucius Temple was completed in 1666.
1666 年 完 成 了 孔 廟
Existing schools were changed to Han schools.
學 校 變 成 漢 學 堂
Aborigines who used Roman scripts
原 來 使 用 羅 馬 拼 音
and practiced the Christian faith
崇 拜 基 督 的 原 住 民
had to relearn Han culture.
又 開 始 學 習 漢 文 化
In 1651, Cheng's general Shih Lang betrayed Cheng
1651 年 鄭 軍 將 領 施 琅
and surrendered to the Ching Dynasty due to his
困 為 與 鄭 成 功 的 恩 怨
resentment against Cheng Cheng-kung.
而 叛 鄭 降 清
Cheng Cheng-kung had put Shih's father to the sword.
鄭 成 攻 下 令 格 殺 施 琅 的 父 親
To avenge his father,
施 琅 為 報 殺 父 之 仇
Shih continued to write and urge
從 此 不 斷 上 蔣
the Ching Emperor to attack Taiwan.
向 清 廷 建 言 言 攻 打 台 灣
In June 1683,
1683 年 6 月
the Ching administration accepted Shih's proposal to attack Taiwan.
清 廷 援 受 施 琅 攻 台 主 張
Shih led 200 ships to invade Pescadores.
施 琅 率 領 兩 百 多 觼 船 攻 下 澎 湖
Cheng Ko-shuang, son of Cheng Ching, surrendered to the Ching Emperor,
鄭 經 之 子 鄭 克 堵 投 降 清 帝 國
thus ending the “Cheng dynasty”
繼 橫 海 上 長 達 半 世 紀 的
that had dominated the seas for half a century.
﹁ 鄭 氏 王 朝 」 正 式 走 入 歷 史
On Dec. 22, 1683
1683 年 12 月 22 日
Shih wrote the Ching Emperor
施 琅 上 疏 康 熙 皇 帝
strongly opposing the decision to abandon Taiwan.
強 恬 反 對 清 廷 放 棄 台 灣
In 1684, the Ching Dynasty
1684 年 清 廷 正 式 把 台 灣
incorporated Taiwan into its domain.
納 入 清 帝 國 版 圖
Since the late 17th century,
自 17 世 紀 末 開 始
the Han Chinese's notion of “Taiwan island”
漢 人 對 ﹁ 台 灣 島 」 的 稱 呼
gradually extended from Anping in Tainan
透 漸 從 台 南 安 平
to Tainan County and City,
擴 大 到 台 南 縣 市
and lastly, to the entire island.
最 後 擴 大 到 全 島
During the early days of its rule,
清 常 國 治 台 初 期
the Ching administration adopted
清 政 府 對 ﹁ 台 灣 」
an attitude toward Taiwan, this small island overseas,
這 座 孰 懸 海 外 的 小 島
that was different from its rule of the mainland
採 取 不 同 於 大 陸 的 治 理 態 度
To prevent immigrants from causing trouble,
為 了 防 範 移 民 作 亂
it issued proclamations to restrict
特 別 頒 布 ﹁ 渡 台 禁 令 」
coastal residents in Fuchien and Kuangtung
防 止 福 建
from illegally immigrating to Taiwan.
廣 東 的 沿 海 居 民 偷 渡
Yet
但 是
the waves of immigrants could not be halted.
仍 然 無 法 阻 擋 這 股 移 民 浪 潮
Han immigrants continued
前 仆 後 繼 的 漢 人 移 民
to risk their lives to cross the Black Water Ditch to
冒 著 九 死 一 生 橫 渡 黑 水 溝
come to the island paradise
從 唐 山 來 到 台 灣 這 座
of Taiwan
海 上 ﹁ 蓬 萊 仙 島 」
in search for better lives.
尋 找 新 天 地
Formosa, once rich in oceanic culture
原 本 充 滿 海 洋 文 化
and international flavors,
及 國 際 色 彩 的 福 爾 摩 沙
became quickly immersed in mainland culture.
從 此 急 速 含 大 陲 文 化 傾 斡
It was the beginning of the 300-year
開 啟 至 今 超 過 三 百 年 的
Han Chinese culture era in Taiwan.
台 灣 漢 文 化 紀 元